The world we live in today is a global world. We no longer conduct business solely within
one country. Our applications must make the transition from one country to another seamlessly.
The XPG standards are defining what services must be available to affect this transition.
This process is called internationalisation. This involves the display and printing of
characters, both common ones and ones unique to individual languages, the format of date
and monetary fields, and the collating sequence of the characters.
Now, to get a better grip on this, let's first off define some terms. A character set is the set of
characters that you see on your keyboards or your printers that you can print. Internally,
those characters are represented by unique hexadecimal values in memory. The relationship
between the hexadecimal value and the character diagram is defined in a list called a code page.
ZOS itself has no support for code pages. TSO-ISBF has support for code pages like ZOS-UNIX,
but differently. Each country and region might also have a unique code page called the country
extended code page, which relates the hexadecimal values from 00 to FF into a character set with
the different characters used, including the needed letters in that language.
Data coming from ZOS datasets or from a workstation could be in any of the code pages shown
here. The special characters shown here are the 14 variant characters that are often different
between the code pages. The individual country extended code page includes characters
letters in their alphabets that also require unique considerations. This diagram illustrates
some of the problems you meet in an international environment. Let's look at the various
translation issues and some solutions. First, let's look at a relatively simple situation
in a USA environment. Here are some possibilities to consider. Customize your keyboard using the
features of the emulator to create the correct hexadecimal coding for the characters.
If you are a TSO user, specify the omvsconvert parameter when you enter the shell.
If you are using the zos-unix shell through the TCPIPR login or telnet support,
use the chcp shell command to convert from ASCII to the zos-unix code page.
And when using oput, oget and ocopy, use the convert parameters on these statements.
But what about shell scripts and translation with international character sets?
Since many shell scripts use special characters, they must run the code page they were created
with. This means that users in other countries have to have their own translated copy of the
script or they'll have to change to the code page that goes with the script.
The icopy command can be used to translate the scripts from one code page to another.
Here you see that hash sign is represented as something else when you change the code page.
This character has a special meaning in a shell script. If this character is changed to something
else, well, the shell script will not work as it should. This visual illustrates the
problem from another angle. Here is a script with 3270 emulator program in IBM
1047 USA code page and IBM 277 Danish code page. These are all things to watch out for
when using international character sets. Let's wrap this up with a comparison of
different functions in TSO and the Unix shell. Command processing in the shell is similar to
command processing for C lists. In combination with the shell utilities, the shell provides
a programming environment as rich as the REX environment in COS. Hierarchical files can be
edited from COS using ISPF menus. The ISPF menus can be invoked by the TSO commands OEdit
and OBrowse. In the shell, the editor can be used to edit HFS files. In COS, SDSF is used to
monitor and control batch jobs. The TSOE commands status, cancel and output can also be used.
In the shell, there are multiple commands to control jobs including PS,
jobs, kill, FG, BG and wait. Background jobs are submitted by the TSOE commands submit
in a ZOS environment. In the shell, a command ended with an ampersand, runs in the background.
You can also use the shell submit command. Now in the next module,
we'll move on to address functions in COS Unix.